Welcome back, in this lesson we're going to learn about function signatures and TypeScript.
Function signatures let us describe what a function should like, in other words its shape,
with its parameters and return type, without worrying about the implementation.
This becomes incredibly useful for callbacks, APIs, and things like large applications.
So imagine you're working with functions that are passed around, like callbacks or perhaps event handlers.
So how do we make sure that every function follows the same structure?
We want to make sure that we have the same parameters, the same return type, and things like type safety, of course.
This is exactly what function signatures solve.
So a function signature describes the parameters that the function accepts, the types of those parameters,
and the type of value that a function returns.
And effectively it's, as I said, to find this shape of a function.
So let's do a very simple example, and we're going to have a function.
Add, and it is going to have two parameters, a number, b, number,
and it's going to return a number.
So we can use the arrows, syntax, and say number.
This line itself doesn't actually define the function yet, but it does define what the function must look like.
In other words, it's shape that we have two parameters, and we have a return type.
Now we can assign a function that matches that signature.
To this line, it's up doesn't have to find a function yet, it just defines what the function must look like.
We could do now to add equals x and y parameter, and then we'd have find immensation by saying x plus y.
To now assign a function, here, that actually matches the signature.
If we then try an assign a function that doesn't match the signature,
TypeScript's going to throw us nearer.
Now instead of repeating signatures all the time, we can create a type alias for this function.
Let's just remove this for the second to type, and type is a math operation,
a number, and b, number, and our math operation returns a number.
Now we can reuse this function signature any way we like, and we can define different functions to use this math operation.
So we could do const multiply, for example, and our multiply function is going to use this type of math operation.
We take the two parameters, a and b, and then we define the implementation of that function,
so we could say a times b. We could then reuse this, and so you const subtract,
this is also a math operation, take the same two parameters, and then we define the implementation,
so we say a minus b. And then we can keep on like add and divide, etc.
So you're going to find that function signatures are extremely common with callbacks.
So let's just click to find an example of a callback to function calculate
to a number, a number, now we also want to pass in an operation, and say operation,
and the operation is going to accept two numbers, x and y, and the operation is going to return
a number, and this is going to be all part of our definition for our calculate.
Now all we need to do is to return our operation, and we can execute our operation, whatever it is,
the implementation, by just doing operation a b. This guarantees that the callback function,
the operation here, has the correct parameters and return type, and we can call it like this,
we can do calculate, pass some numbers, perhaps 10 and 5, and then we define our callback function,
x and y, and we say what we want with it, so we can say x plus y, for example,
or we might want to do the same thing again, take the calculate, and this time we're going to
change it rather than x plus y, let's say x divided by y. Now to make this even cleaner,
we could extract the signature. But the top here, I'm going to define a type of operation,
operation has been going to have two numbers, A and B, and returns an number, just like we had
before, but our operation, rather than defining it like this, we can now use the type of operation,
remove this and say our operation is a type operation,
and then we can just call it in the same way, so you can see that it's a much
meter in the easier to define a type here, and just use that inside our callback for our
callback function. Innovators can also define function signatures, but let's have an interface, and interface
could be perhaps logger, and they're going to have message type string, and that's going to return
to nothing, so basically avoid. This interface itself describes a function, but not an object,
so let's now have the implementation of that and do const, perhaps log, message, this takes
or is ill type logger, where we provide the message, and now you can give the actual implementation
of that, which is simply console log, and then message.
Function signatures can also include optional parameters.
So again, as an example, let's do type greet, this has a name string age,
to number, and that's going to return a string, and we want to make the age option off,
that's why I put the question mark in here, if we didn't have the question mark, that would be
mandatory, so let's just leave it as an optional, so this means our age may or may not be provided,
of course, so now let's actually try news this by doing const greet of type greet. Now we're
going to take our two parameters name and age, and now we can actually give it the implementation,
so if we have an age, age is present, we're then going to do a simple string of say hello,
dollar name, age is dollar age. Otherwise, we just simply do our normal hello, so hello,
dollar name, and you're going to find very typically that function signatures are pretty much
everywhere in UI frameworks, and the most typical example of this is by having a click handler,
on the vent, and in particular mouse event, then if we do type, perhaps click, and let
whoops click, and there, this could be like the event mouse event, for example, and that's going
to return a point, and this is a very typical definition for a click handler,